# 大家好 最近老是下雨 這個池塘的水都快溢出來啦
Hi everyone! It's always raining recently. The water in the pond will be overflowing very soon.
# 我把它 那個修一下 修好一點 別讓魚給跑啦
Let me fix it, get it fixed. I'm not gonna let the fish run away.
# 在這裡 在這裡好多魚的哦
Here, here are a lot of fish, you know.
# 不知道有沒有跑掉
Let's see if they've run away.
# 你看 上次我放的那幾條紅鯉魚
Look! These are the couple of red carps that I put here last time.
# 還在那裡
They're still there.
# 兩條
Two are,
# 黑的
black.
# 兩條紅的
And two are red.
# 剛好我看一下蛇頭魚 好大的
I just saw a snakehead fish, a very big one.
# 跑哪裡去了
Where is it now?
# 我原以為它們跑了 原來沒跑 你看
I thought they had run away, but they haven't, look!
# 現在吃的好肥呀 它們
They're really fat now.
# 這個魚我們從來不用喂的
These fish don't need to be fed at all.
# 就吃
They only,
# 吃一些那些草啊 吃一些那些
they only feed on the grass, or, like,
# 小魚小蝦 就可以了
small fish, small shrimps, that's it.
# 你看 那幾條鯉魚
Look! The couple of fish over there
# 應該跑了一些 我放了不止那麼一點點的
I think some have already run away. I've put more than just a tiny little bit here.
# 我先把這個水堵一下
Let me block the waterflow first.
# 把這個水稍微堵高一點
I'm gonna make a higher block.
# 我把這個石頭
This rock...
# 多撈一點起來
I want more rocks.
# 修一下這個口
Let me block this exit.
# 魚就跑不出去啦
Then the fish can't run away.
# 差不多啦
Almost there
# 你看
Look!
# 現在就可以啦
It's alright now.
# 搞的太累了
It's so tiring!
# 我去山上看一下有沒有那個萢子
Let me go onto the hill and see if there are any, you know,
# 萢子吃
any berries.
# 你看這個竹子
Have a look at this bamboo!
# 一個月長那麼高啦
It has become that tall in just one month.
# 應該十多米啦
It should be more than 10 metres now.
# 再過一兩個月的話就長成那個
In one or two months, it will be,
# 正常的竹子一樣那麼大
as big as the bamboos that we usually see.
# 好啦 摘點 摘點萢子吃 好口渴
Alright! Let's pick some, pick some berries. I'm really thirsty.
# 你看 這個就是蛇莓哦
Look! This is called, snake berry.
# 像草莓一樣的 這個是不能吃的
It looks like a strawberry, but it's not edible.
# 有毒的哦 這個
It's poisonous, you know.
# 你看 這裡很多哦
Look! Here are a lot!
# 但是還沒熟
But they're not yet ripe.
# 有點酸酸的 等它熟了我再過來
They're a bit sour now. I'll come again when they become ripe.
# 你看 這裡好多
Look! Here are a lot!
# 還一是很熟 這裡也有一個
But they're still a bit green. Here's another one.
# 你看 這樣的都還不是很熟
Look! It's still a bit green,
# 有點酸
and it's a bit sour.
# 你看 這樣的
Look! Here they are.
# 再過幾天就熟了
They will become ripe in a few days.
# 萢子沒找到哦 看到這裡有點石榴花
I can't find any berries. But I see some pomegranate flowers here.
# 我搞點石榴花來吃一下 (註︰直譯會變成"get some XXX to eat"，這說法太奇怪，改一下)
These flowers can quench my thirst.
# 石榴花裡面有很多水份的
These flowers are really juicy.
# 哇 這
Wa! It's a,
# 90度的坡 怎麼上
a vertical slope. How can I get onto it?
# 你看 我就拉了 拉了在這裡吃了
Look! I just pull it, pull it down and have my feast here.
# 那不然那個
Otherwise, you know,
# 會把這個樹搞斷的
I would break the branch.
# 搞斷了明年就沒得吃了
If I broke it, it wouldn't be here anymore next year.
# 可以哦
It's not bad.
# 酸酸甜甜
Sweet and sour
# 吃之前要看一下啊 看有沒有蟲
You need to take a look, and see if there are any bugs, before putting it into your mouth.
# 哇 口渴的時候也可以解一下渴 這個
Wa! It can really quench thirst, you know.
# 嗯 這個不好 (註︰沒有原字幕)
Um! This one is no good.
# 快謝了的就不要了
Don't take it if it's about to wither.
# 拉下來
Pull it down.
# 你看這個象草 都長出來啦
Look! The elephant grass is already growing out.
# 一片綠綠的
It's green everywhere.
# 很靚哦
So beautiful!
# 去年 去年霜的死的時候 這杆都打沒啦
When they were killed, killed by the frost last year, nothing was left, not even the stems.
# 現在又長出來啦
And they're growing out now.
# 第一年種下去的 你看
It's my first time planting them, look!
# 一輩子都不用種了
And it's also my last time.
# 誒呀 好多竹子
Aya! A lot of bamboos
# 這是兄弟家種的香菇
These are my buddy's shiitake mushrooms.
# 一個都沒有
Not even one is left.
# 一個都沒看到
I can't see any, not even one.
# 太可憐了 一個都沒有
Nothing is left, what a pity!
# 哎呀 有一個
Aya! Here's one!
# 沒啦 就一個
Just one, no more.
# 兄弟在不在
Is my buddy around?
# 拿回去打湯 就一個
Just one. I'll use it to make soup.
# 啊 好香啊 你看這香菇 很漂亮吧
Ah! It smells so good. Have a look at this mushroom. It's really pretty, isn't it?
# 好啦 今天 今天的視頻就到這裡啦 (註︰要對應一下第一次的「今天」發音不準確)
Alright! Tha, the video ends here.
# 兩手空空 甚麼都沒有
We're leaving, empty-handed, with nothing at all.
# 你看 這是我家的雞
Look! These are my chickens.